Bill Kremer, CSP

Minneapolis, Minnesota, 55406, USA

Safety and Health Program Specialist with expertise across multiple industries. Handson partner with executive-level management to front-line production employees to ensure complete and effective implementation of safety best practices. Safety training including "why" and verification of understanding. Development of comprehensive safety programs integrated into work processes.

Certification

Certified Safety Professional, Board of Certified Safety Professionals, since 2009

Experience

Senior Safety Engineer

2011 – Present

Donaldson Company, Incorporated, Bloomington, Minnesota, USA

Manufacturer of industrial, large engine, and electronics air filtration and engine fluids filtration. Over 12,000 employees in more than 40 countries.

Primary safety resource for all USA manufacturing locations.

Technical expert for first two USA sites achieving OHSAS 18001 Certification.

Occupational Health and Safety compliance auditing for multiple USA and Global locations, including China, South Africa and Australia.

Routine performance of air contaminant and noise sampling to ensure compliance with local, regional and national regulatory limits.

Use of LEAN manufacturing techniques to incorporate health and safety into production processes.

Occupational Safety & Health Consultant

2010 - 2011

Consultant for Milk Specialties Global, Fond du Lac, Wisconsin and other locations

Manufacturer of milk protein food products

Performed Occupational Safety and Health Surveys to help employers identify, prioritize, and eliminate or reduce hazards in their workplaces.

Developed site and process specific safety procedures including Lockout / Tagout and Confined Space Entry.

Performed safety training based on employer-specific policies and actual workplace hazards.

Corporate Safety Program Manager 2008 - 2010

Nash Finch Company, Edina, Minnesota, USA

Fortune 500 wholesale food distribution company with over 7500 employees working in 20 distribution centers and 60 retail stores.

Provided direction and resources for site management to create and foster a safety culture.

Spearheaded the creation of a Fleet Safety program for more than 400 company truck drivers by working cooperatively with fleet management, dispatchers and drivers.

Created training materials and tools to effectively train employees and supervisors in both distribution warehouses and retail stores, including Powered Industrial Truck Training, Incident Investigation, Safe Lifting, Protective Footwear, and Ergonomic Best Practices.

Performed safety audits at grocery distribution warehouses and retail stores, and worked with site management to develop action plans and solutions.

Developed improved safety metrics for both distribution warehouses and retail stores.

Bill Kremer, CSP

	Industrial Hygiene Engineer / Health Investigator 2000 - 2008
	Minnesota Occupational Safety and Health Administration (OSHA), Department of Labor and Industry, Saint Paul, Minnesota, USA
	Regulating agency, responsible for workplace safety and health of all Minnesota workers.
	Conducted over 270 complaint, programmed, and accident investigations, including Process Safety Management assessments and industrial hygiene evaluations in numerous work environments, including metal fabrication, plastic injection molding operations, food processing, concrete manufacturing, woodworking facilities and construction sites.
	Wrote reports for each investigation including legally defensible citations and participated in their defense during settlement agreements.
	Attended extensive safety and health training courses at the OSHA Training Institutes.
	Participated on the MNOSHA Process Safety Management (PSM) Team, reviewing compliance direction and advising employers on PSM issues.
	Provided stakeholder service via email, letter and telephone regarding standard interpretation and industrial hygiene issues.
Education	B.S. Chemical Engineering
	Michigan Technological University, Houghton, Michigan, USA
Professional	American Society of Safety Engineers - Northwest Chapter
Membership	
Computer	Microsoft Macintosh MS Word MS Excel MS PowerPoint MS Access MS Project MS SharePoint WordPerfect Lotus Notes GroupWise OpenOffice.org